你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院内存错误模块的第2个视频
welcome to video 2 of the memory errors module of pwn college
我是Yan，今天我们要谈论的是
I'm Yan and today we're going to be talking about
使用问题导致的内存错误
high level problems that lead to memory errors
在之前的视频中我讲过
as a reminder in the previous video I talked about how
丹尼斯·里奇
Dennis Ritchie
幻灯片右边的这个人
this man on the right of the slide here
创建了C编程语言
created the C programming language
他创建它是为了为Unix操作系统编写程序
he created it to create utilities for the Unix operating system
unix是他在这之前与别人合作创建的
which he had co created just several years earlier
C语言的设计兼顾了对底层的控制和
and C was designed to give low level control and power to the developer
让程序员能够写出高效的代码
to allow them to write fast code
同时只要使用便捷的高级语言 的能力
but still use a source code a high level language to write it
而不是直接用汇编写
rather than writing it directly in assembly
不幸的是，与冯·诺依曼架构的结合
unfortunately in combination in a way with the Von Neumann architecture
带来了图像左边的三个约翰
brought to us by the three Johns on these figures on the left um
以及冯命名的结构
and von nominement's architectures
看起来有点不考虑安全问题
kind of seeming thoughtlessness about security
C语言的兴起和惊人的传播导致了一个状态
the rise and amazing spread of C has led to a state
直到今天，我们仍然被内存错误所困扰
where we are plagued with memory errors and software even now to this day
那么让我们来看看导致这些错误的一些使用问题
so let's look at some of the high level problems  that lead to these errors
整体上最大的问题
the biggest problem kind of the overall
是C信任开发人员
general summary is that C trusts the developer
在python中
in python
如果你创建一个包含三个元素的列表
if you create a list of with three elements in it
你试着访问第11个元素
and you try to access the 11th element
python会告诉你不行
python will tell you no
这个列表只有三个元素
this list only has three elements
你不能访问第11个元素
you're not accessing the 11th
绝对不可能
absolutely no way
它会抛出一个异常
um it'll throw an exception
然后你就会意识到
and uh then you will realize oh
我正在访问一个我不应该访问的元素
I'm accessing an element that I shouldn't be accessing
你可以修改你的代码
and you can fix your code
C不会那样做
C won't do that
事实上，C不能那样做
in fact C cannot do that
C被设计成
C is designed again
要尽可能和汇编对应
to be as low level as as direct translation as possible
C语言只是让你不用再为寄存器管理操心了
all C really does is take the burden of register management away from you
并且在函数调用等方面更便捷
and handle calling functions and so forth in a nicer way than assembly might
你可以创建数据结构等等
let you create structures and etc etc
当然c做了很多
of course c does a lot
但是C语言不会去隐式记录
but what C doesn't do is implicitly track things
比如数组中元素的数量
like the number of elements in an array
如果您想跟踪数组中元素的数量
if you want to track the number of elements in an array
在访问数组之前，要注意不要越界访问
and be very careful to check if the array is big enough before you access it
当然你可以用C来实现一个这样的功能
of course you can write that in C
您可以创建一个同时具有数组和大小的结构
you can create a structure that has both an array and a size
但现实上
but realistically
如果人们不这样做
if people do not do that and
它们只是?？的访问内存 C允许这样
they just access memory ？？ C will let them do that
问题就会出现
and problems will arise
会出现的问题
the problems that will arise
和我要讲的其他使用问题有关系
have to do with some of these other high level problem causes that I'll talk about
首先
to begin with
C将控制信息和数据混合在一起
C mixes control information and data in the same place
你应该
you should be um
应该记得栈
should remember the stack
你们已经学过了，希望做了之前逆向的课后题
you Learned about it and hopefully had to deal with it a lot in the previous module in reverse engineering
栈保存了大量的用户数据
the stack holds a lot of user data
我的意思是有用户数据
I mean there's user data
实际上，栈一开始保存了大量的用户数据
actually the stack starts out holding a lot of user data
用户数据在程序执行过程
but user data throughout executional program
传的到处都是
spreads all over the place
不幸的是
unfortunately
在相同的内存区域
in those same general memory regions
程序存储大量的控制信息
programs store a lot of control information
他们把这些控制数据和普通数据存储在一起
and they store this together with the non controlled data that
包括用户数据
including user data that is stored
以栈为例
recall the stack for example
栈上的所有东西都混在一起
everything on the stack is to jumble together
函数在栈上有包含了返回地址的函数栈帧
functions have their function frames on the stack containing the return address
我们开始吧
or let's start actually
从左边开始
from the left here
函数的局部变量
the local variables of the active function
其中一些是用户控制的，可能是攻击者控制的
some of which are user controlled potentially attacker controlled
指向内存中其他位置的指针
saved pointers to other places in memory
例如，指向栈中别的位置的基指针
for example the saved base pointer for the stack points elsewhere in the stack
指向代码段的指针
save pointers to code
稍后用于从函数返回的指针
pointers that are later used to return from the function
而且
and
再向右一点，再往上一点
further to the right and the stack further up the stack
调用方函数的局部变量
local variables of the caller function
调用当前函数的函数
the function that called that function
调用调用方函数的函数，依此类推
the function that called that function and so on
栈上有很多数据
there's a lot of data on the stack and it's all
储存在一起，处理方式完全相同
store together and it's all treated exactly the same
具有严重的安全影响
which is has serious secured implications
前面我们讨论了访问3元素数组的第11个元素
earlier we talked about accessing the 11th element of 3 element array
当你在C语言中这样做时会
what happens when you do that in C
如果你的本地缓冲区是一个数组
if your local buffer is this a array
你最终会访问这里的某个地方
you end up accessing somewhere in here
并且直接往那里写入数据
and writing data directly there
这是个坏消息
that's really bad news right
你能利用它做很多事
what can you do with that you can do a lot with that
例如，你可以获取一个返回地址
you can for example take a return address
指向程序.text代码段的某个地方
that was pointing somewhere in the .text segment section into the code of the program
然后把它指向别的地方
and change it to point somewhere else
比如将其更改为指向你注入的shellcode
or change it to point to some shell code that you injected
如果您还记得shellcode模块
if you recall the shellcoding module
这是个大问题
this is a big problem
事实上，在一个阳光明媚的日子这个问题
and in fact this problem on one sunny day
起码在1988年地球的某个地方可能是晴朗的
probably was sunny somewhere in 1988
罗伯特·泰彭·莫里斯利用了
Robert tepen Morris used this exact situation
一个基于堆栈的缓冲区溢出
a stack based buffer overflow where
他从栈缓冲区溢出
he overflowed from some buffer on the stack
并且覆盖了返回地址
and and overwrote the return address
据我所知，他创建了第一个有记录的内存破坏漏洞利用
he used this to create the 1st documented memory corruption exploit as far as I know
推出了第一款蠕虫病毒，搞瘫了整个网络
launched the 1st designed worm and brought down the entire net
我们在讲shellcode的时候讲过这个
we talked about this back when we talked about shellcoding
这正是他意外创造这么大危害所利用的漏洞
but these are the exact bugs that he used to do all this damage accidentally
损失是如此之大
the damage was so great that
互联网基本上被关闭
the internet had to be basically shut down disconnected
修好所有的机器
fixed all of the machines
然后再接入网络
and then plug back in
想象一下，现在这么做简直是疯了
imagine doing that now it would be insane
对于这个
for this
当然我之前提到过
of course I mentioned before
他被根据1986年的计算机欺诈和滥用法案定罪
he was convicted under the 1986 computer fraud and abuse act
但我没有提到他后来成了一名计算机科学教授
but I didn't mention that he has since become a CS professor
麻省理工学院的计算机科学教授
computer science professor at MIT and
联合创立了combinator和其他一些企业
co founded y combinator and a bunch of other ventures
所以他过得很好
so he is doing quite well
尽管他有不光彩的过去
despite his shady past
好，我们接着看问题三
all right let's move on to problem 3 right
C混合了控制数据和非控制数据
C mixes control data non control data
以同样的方式C混合了数据和元数据
in the same way C mixes data and metadata
这也是有问题的
right and this is also problematic
非常相似，但也有问题
very similar but also problematic
最简单的例子是字符串
considered the simplest example is strings
你们都应该知道字符串是以null结尾的
you should all know strings are null terminated
在C语言中，当你有一个字符串时，比如
in C when you have a string you say you know
名字叫Yan
the name is Yan
在这个例子中，初始值为Yan的10个字符数组
in this case this 10 character array with initial value of Yan
占了10个字节
hold 10 bytes
Yan和7个空字节
Yan and then 7 null bytes
其中三个字节是数据y a和n
three of these bytes are data y a and n
null字节实际上是元数据
and the null byte actually is metadata
它表示，嘿，这是字符串的结尾
it encodes it says hey this is the end of the string
这简单地编码了字符串的大小
this simplicitly encodes the size of the string
只使用一个字节
using just a single byte right
字符串的大小基本上是
and the size of the string is basically
字符串的开始
the beginning of the string
直到null字节所在的位置
up to where the null byte is
这是有问题的
this is problematic
考虑一下，假如你用read获取一个名称
consider if you are just inputting a name using the read system call that just gets a bunch of data
你可以这样做
and you do something like
从标准输入读入数据到名称变量
read from standard input into name
有一个C宏，它能获取变量大小
and then there's a macro C that gives you the size of a variable
比如名字的大小
say the size of name
乍一看，这很合理
this this looks reasonable at 1st glance
但
but
有一些问题
there are some problems
首先，这允许用户在任何他们想要的地方注入空字节
1st of all it allows a user to inject null bytes anywhere they want
read会接受他们
read will happily take them
所以我可以用一个空字节来代替Yan的a
so I could put a null byte instead of the a of the Yan
突然不是一个10长度的字符串
and suddenly instead of a 10 length string
我在一堆其他数据中输入了1个长度的字符串
I have inputted 1 length string in a bunch of other data
其现状值得怀疑
the status of which is questionable
因为任何字符串操作都会在空字节上终止
because any string operations will terminate on that null byte
同样，如果没有空字节会怎样
likewise what if there are no null bytes
这更糟糕
this is even worse
如果我把10个变量都填满
if I just fill all 10 variables
所有10个字节，不好意思，那个变量数据
all 10 bytes excuse me and that variable with data
这个字符串有多长？
how long is that string
C不存储长度信息
C as a reminder stores no other length information
它不可能知道这是
it has no way to know that this is
在编译完代码之后，它没有办法知道
after compiling the code it has no way to know
这里应是10字节长
that this used to be 10 bytes long
接下来对这个变量的操作
so further operations on this variable
因为缺乏空字节记录字符串的长度
lacking that null byte encodes its length that the strings length
可能会做一些奇怪和疯狂的事情
might do weird and crazy things
好的，最后一个使用问题
alright final high level problem will cover
初始化和清理
um initialization and cleanup right
C是非常接近底层的
again C is very low level
除非你让它做
unless you tell it to
否则它不会进行任何初始化
it will not do any initialization
或者任何的清理工作
or mostly any cleanup
就清理而言，它所做的就是
all it will do in terms of cleanup for example is
抬高栈指针来打引号的释放栈帧
add to your stack pointer to quote unquote deallicate the stack frame
我在上一模块讲过
and I talked about in the previous module
释放栈帧实际上不删除任何数据
how deallicate the stack frame doesn't actually remove any data
在清理阶段C只是移动栈指针
in the cleanup stage C just moves the stack pointer
那些旧数据还在那里
that old data still there
只是现在在栈指针的左边
it's just now to the left of the stack pointer
所以它不会
so it doesn't
真正概念上存在于正常的程序操作中
really conceptually exist in normal program operation
但它还在那里
but it's still there
如果程序中有内存错误，仍然可以访问它
you might still be able to access it if there was a memory error in the program
同样的
likewise
对于初始化
initialization
它不会初始化任何东西，除非你告诉它
so you won't initialize anything unless you tell it to
除非你显式地初始化它
unless you explicitly initialize it
看看这个例子
if you look at this example
有一个字符数组叫 myVariable
there's a character array called my variable
它大小为8
and it's of size 8
当我开始
when I start
当这个程序启动时
when this program launches
抱歉，当这个函数被调用时
sorry when this function is called
myVariable的值是多少
what will be the value of my variable
它不会是空
it won't be nulls
在前面的例子中，我设置了初始值
in the previous example I had this initial value
这是显式地将myName初始化为内存中的这个值
this is an initialization that explicitly initialized my name to this value in memory
这个没有初始值
this has no initial value
我相信你也用c代码试过
and I'm sure that you have created code in C
它也没有初始值
that had no initialization either
不初始化
without initialization
它只会是恰好在那里的值
it will simply have the value that happened to be there
前一个函数在栈上留下的值
on the stack left over by a previous function
你可以试试
you can try it
创建一个这样的程序
create a program like this
运行它，看看它会告诉你什么
run it and see what it tells you
实际上，在以后的视频中会更深入地讨论它
actually you'll also go through it in the future video more in depth
但它是C程序面临的一个主要问题
but it is a major issue facing C programs
这些就是主要的形式问题
so these are the form major problems
初始化
initialization
元数据、控制数据
metadata control data
和开发者搬起石头砸自己脚的能力
and basically the ability of a developer to shoot themselves in the foot
有可能编写安全的C代码吗？完全可以
is it possible to write secure C code absolutely
C并不是一种不安全的语言
it's not that C is an insecure language
C只是提供了以不安全的方式使用它
C gives you the tools to use it in an insecure way
如果你真的想
if you so want to do um
这是我希望你们从这门课中学到的一点
that's kind of one takeaway I'd like you to take from this course
另一个结论
the other takeaway
或者从这个模块
or from this module
另一个结论是
the other takeaway though
在很多很多很多情况下
is in many many many many cases
C和其他低级语言非常非常容易被误用
it is very very very very easy to misuse C and other low level languages
最终会创建不安全的代码
in a way that ends up in the creation of insecure code
之后的视频见
I'll see you in future videos of this module
我们将深入探讨
we'll go in depth into
几个不同的内存破坏的例子
a couple of different examples of memory corruption
然后我们会谈到
and then we'll talk about
内存损坏的缓解措施
mitigations of memory corruptions